Herbert C. Hunsaker Papers
Herbert C. Hunsaker Papers
1920-1984
Hunsaker, Herbert Cason, 1891-
20 linear ft.
Hunsaker was involved in adult education for over sixty years. Papers include brochures, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets, reports, speeches, audiorecordings of interviews, and materials related to Hunsaker's thesis. Best represented are the dissertation materials, his international activities with World Education, U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and UNESCO, and his activities related to professional conferences and seminars. Of interest are the papers related to his China and Middle East tours. Significant correspondents include Rewi Allen, George E. Davis, Thomas B. Keehn, Paul Sheats, and Hunsaker's family. Among the personal papers are those concerning Hermann H. Field, for whom Hunsaker acted as absentee executor.
149426
Biographical History
Herbert Cason Hunsaker's involvement with adult education spanned over sixty years. His work led him to the Middle East and to China, as well as most of the United States. Hunsaker was active in many professional organizations and civic groups. In 1967, he was President of the Adult Education Association (AEA). He was also instrumental in the establishment of the China Tour Committee of the AEA, along with the International Associates. He made a great many speeches to a variety of adult educators, students, and to the general public.
His interests and concerns were centered around three themes: internationalism; school and community relations; and continuing education. These three interests intertwined throughout his life.
Hunsaker began his professional career as a college administrator at University of Newark (Rutgers University) in 1926, then worked his way up to Dean of Adult Education at Cleveland College. During his time at Cleveland Hunsaker worked for Unesco, along with serving in the army during World War II. Taking a leave of absence from Cleveland College, he returned to Teacher's College at Columbia University, where he had earned his M.A. in 1928, to work on a doctorate in education. It is not clear whether he earned the PhD, but in 1955 he returned to academe as Professor of Adult Education and Assistant Director, Division of Adult Education, Purdue University. This was his last academic position.
In 1962 Hunsaker took a leave of absence from Purdue University until 1964 when he retired. From 1962 to 1965 he was a United States Agency for International Development (USAID), Adult Education Advisor stationed in Turkey. From 1965 to 1969 he did the same in Afghanistan. In 1965, as an interim assignment, Dr Hunsaker was loaned by USAID to Unesco Fundamental and Literacy Education Division for two months to help plan a pilot project in Functional Literacy for Pakistan.
Hunsaker retired from USAID in 1969. He then worked for World Education as a Consultant and Field Representative in literacy planning education. This was an AID sponsored and financed project headquartered at Literacy House, Lucknow, India. While on this assignment Hunsaker traveled throughout the Middle East, the Philippines, and Thailand. He held this position until 1972 when he retired for a third time.
In 1972 Herbert and Marion Hunsaker returned to their home in West Lafayette, Indiana. Continuing to work as a part-time consultant for World Education and the International Council of Adult Education, the Hunsakers at once began another project which was a series of tours sponsored by the AEA China Tour Committee and by the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) of both the Middle East and China. The Hunsakers led a fourth, and possibly a fifth tour.
Hunsaker Chronology
1898: Born, White Salmon, Washington
1922: A.B. Univ of Washington
1928: M.A. Columbia
1937: LL.B. Univ of Newark (Rutgers)
1926-39: Asst to President, Registrar, Assoc Dean, and Prof of Adult Education, Univ of Newark.
1939-41: Field representative AAAE
1941-55: Dean Cleveland College (Western Reserve Univ)
1942: Bureau of Special Operations, Office of War Information
1949: U.S.delegate to International Conf on Adult Education (Denmark)
1949: Member of UNESCO's Consultative Comm on Fundamental and Adult Education
1955: PhD from Columbia University [?]
1955-62: Professor of Adult Education and Asst Dir, Div of Adult Education, Purdue University
1960: President of Adult Education Association
1961-69: Near East-South Asia Division, USAID
1962-65: Adult Education Advisor, USAID, Turkey
1962-64: Leave of absence from Purdue University
1965-69: Education Advisor, USAID, Afghanistan
1965: Unesco, Functional Literacy for Pakistan
1969-72: World Education Field Representative
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Herbert C. Hunsaker Papers are largely arranged in the order in which they were found. There was little evidence that it had been rearranged by a third party. Four of the seven series in this collection represent evident categories: Doctoral Theses [DT], Professional Organizations [PROR], Middle East and China Tours, and Personal papers. Three other series were created to deal with material found in files labeled "pending" that were scattered through out the collection or in files with other documents whose labels did not reflect their contents. These are: Correspondence [CORR], Professional [PROF], and Pamphlet files.
The types of materials included in this collection include correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, agenda and minutes, reports, holographic notes, published flyers, brochures and pamphlets, offprints, newspapers clippings, photographs, audio discs, and scrap books.
Documentation related to Hunsaker's activities in professional organizations and institutions of higher education is sparse. Some of these materials may be found in organizational collections such as AEA, or at the institutional archives of Newark University, Cleveland College and Purdue University.
The Doctoral Thesis [DT] material is significant because of the many personal interviews Hunsakar conducted as part of his research. Transcripts of all interviews exist. Audio discs were made for a good number of the interviews.
While attending Teacher's College, Hunsaker taught and attended a number of seminars. Good coverage of this time period can be found in this Professional [PROF] series, which contains materials relating to Hunsaker's activities as an educator and an administrator in institutions of higher education.
Correspondence [CORR] contains both personal (family and friends) and professional (colleagues in adult education, including Paul Sheats).
Professional organizations [PROR] includes correspondence, reports, printed items, and other material from numerous adult education organizations, as well as the US-China Peoples Friendship Association (US-CPFA).
Under the auspices of the Adult Education Association, Hunsaker organized and led a series of tours to the Middle East and China tours between 1976 and 1984 [1985?]. Included here are correspondence, reports, publicity, and evaluations from five of these tours, as well as some unsorted material.
Personal Papers contains photographs, clippings, genealogical files, and other assorted items related to Hunsaker's personal life. It is rich in Hunsaker's opinions about a great many things, and includes material relating to his wife Marion Hunsaker, and Hunsaker's friend Hermann Field who, with several family members, disappeared during a trip to Russia.
Pamphlet files contains a range of printed items -- periodicals, series, newsletters, university and organizational publications, and subject files. At the end of this section are photocopies of pages from several books signed and inscribed to Hunsaker by their authors (for the books themselves, see ).
Arrangement of the Collection
Most of the collection remains in original original order. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Pamphlet files are subdivided by type and arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please to locate additional Hunsaker and/or adult education material.
Separated Material
Three books, signed and inscribed to Hunsaker by their authors, have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Photocopies of the covers and signature/inscription remain in the collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Allen, Rewi, 1897-; Davis, George E.; Field, Hermann H., 1910-; Houle, Cyril O. (Cyril Orvin), 1913-; Hunsaker, Herbert Cason, 1898-; Keehn, Thomas B.; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; Association for Continuing Higher Education (U.S.); Coalition of Adult Education Organizations.; International Council for Adult Education.; Unesco.; United States -- Agency for International Development.; World Education (Organizations: United States); Adult education.; Agendas (administrative records); Sound recordings.; Brochures.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Transcripts.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Herbert Hunsaker, 1984.
Inventory
- Doctoral thesis [DT]
  The files in this series include correspondence, published and unpublished reports, curriculum materials, interview transcripts, teaching notes and course materials, class notes, and manuscript materials relating to Hunsaker's doctoral thesis. The inventory is not a comprehensive description of the contents of this series.
  With a few exceptions, the file headings in this series are Hunsaker's. In some instances file headings have been slightly rewritten for clarity and filing purposes. For example, "Materials & Correspondence from European Trip - Council for Student Travel - 1957" now reads, "Council for Student Travel, 1957." Proper names have been inverted. For example, R.J. Blakely now reads Blakely, R.J. The contents of these files have been left undisturbed.
  The file headings are of several types. There are topical headings, names files, organization files, project titles, and descriptive headings related to Hunsaker's thesis. The Doctoral Thesis series remains in its original order, with the exceptions noted above.
  - Research Materials / Field Trip [RM/FT]
    All material in this sub-series was gathered between 1954 and 1955. Some of the items pre-date 1954. The series is arranged alphabetically by geographic location or institution. The folder titles are Hunsaker's with the exceptions noted above.
    - Field trip itinerary (Box 1)
    - Alabama, correspondence; pamphlets; notes (Box 1)
    - American Council on Education, correspondence, proposal (Box 1)
    - California
      - Correspondence, notes and memorandum; reports; miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Printed materials (Box 1)
    - Clark University, committee minutes (Box 1)
    - Columbia University, nursing service (Box 1)
      See also Institute for Adult Education.
    - Contra Costa Journal College, adult education pamphlets (Box 1)
    - Florida, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Fundamental Education, Board of (Box 1)
    - Georgia Fact Finding Committee, 1938; project proposals (Box 1)
    - Georgia State System of Higher Education (Box 2)
    - Hunter College Community Experience Program (Box 2)
    - Illinois (Box 2)
    - Indiana (Box 2)
    - Kellogg Foundation (Box 2)
    - Michigan State College (Box 2)
    - Oglebay Institute (Box 2)
    - Oregon, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Pennsylvania State University (Box 3)
    - Reed College (Box 3)
    - Springfield College (Box 3)
    - Texas (Box 3)
    - University Adult Education, 1953-1955; correspondence; offprints; speech typescripts [John B. Schwertman; Cyril O. Houle; Paul A. McGhee; Milton S. Eisenhower] (Box 3)
    - University of Chicago (Box 3)
    - University of Georgia, pamphlets and leaflets; "community club" publications; work book for club; correspondence; notes; newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan
      - Correspondence; notes; bulletins; printed reports; minutes (Box 3)
      - Pamphlets; brochures (Box 3)
      - Newsletter; reports and miscellany; annotated bibliography on community councils; press release; telecourse syllabi (Box 3)
    - University of Minnesota, correspondence and notes; questionnaire; report, 1951; promotional literature; typescript history of Bureau of Institutional Research (Box 3)
    - University of Nebraska (Box 4)
    - University of North Carolina, correspondence and notes; reports; conference materials; pamphlets; periodicals; brochure; newspaper offprints (Box 4)
    - University of Oregon, See Oregon.
    - University of Pittsburgh (Box 4)
    - University of Tennessee (Box 4)
    - University of Virginia, correspondence; commencement address, 1947; publicity; Extension Division Bulletin - New Dominion Series, No 118(1950) - No 144 (1953). Incomplete (Box 4)
    - University of Washington
      - Correspondence; notes; reports; interview transcript (Box 4)
      - Assorted printed materials dealing with adult education; clippings (Box 4)
    - University of Wisconsin, correspondence; reports (Bureau of Community Development); pamphlets and brochures; miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Washington State College (Box 4)
    - Western Reserve University, correspondence; offprints; papers; history of School of Medicine; report on adult education; clippings; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Western Reserve University, The Students of Cleveland College, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Interviews [INTV]
    During Hunsaker's field trip across the country he interviewed a good number of adult educators. These interviews were either tape recorded or transcribed by Hunsaker. The transcripts of these interviews went through numerous versions. When Hunsaker finally finished transcribing the interviews they were sent to the interviewees for further correction. Hunsaker also requested permission to use the material for his thesis. Because of the number of iterations each interview went through, there is a redundancy in this series. The files follow his arrangement which is alphabetical by last name.
    - Interviews and taped interviews, pages from thesis and notes (Box 5)
    - Interview recordings
      - Hunsaker interview, unknown, hunsaker_h_001; 4 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Hunsaker interview, unknown, hunsaker_h_002; 4 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Interview "Jess Ogden and Marion"; Jess Ogden, Community Services, Extension Division, University of Virginia, hunsaker_h_003; 4 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview may be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts L to R"
      - Pennsylvania State University: 1. Milton S. Eisenhower, President 2. Edward L. Keller, Director of General Extension & Walter P. Dickinson, Administrative Head, Wilkes-Barre-Scranton Community College, hunsaker_h_004; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for interview can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, folders "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D" and "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts E to K"
      - Pennsylvania State University 1. Stanley H. Campbell, In charge of Division of Community Colleges and Assistant to the Director of General Extension; Side 2. Not Used, hunsaker_h_005; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Pennsylvania State University: 1. Kenneth L. Holderman, Professor and Director of Engineering, School of Engineering; 2. Herbert R. Albrecht, Associate Dean and Director of Agriculture and Home Economics, hunsaker_h_006; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Pennsylvania State University: 1. Fred K. Hochler, Assistant Professor of Political Science in Extension and Ronald Donovan Instructor in Economics, General Extension; Side 2. Not Used, hunsaker_h_007; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Pennsylvania State University: 1. Paul S. Beaver, Supervisor of Management Training, General Extension Division; 2. Paul S. Beaver, Supervisor of Management Training, General Extension Division, 03/23/1954; hunsaker_h_008; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D"
      - Pennsylvania State University: 1. O. R. MacKenzie, Dean, School of Business; 2. M.R. Trabue, Dean, School of Education, 03/22/1954; hunsaker_h_009; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts S to Z"
      - Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio: 1. Joseph T. Wearn, M.D., Dean, School of Medicine, and Professor, and Director, Department of Medicine; 2. Joseph T. Wearn, M.D.; 1. Dr. Ham; 2. Dr. Ham, hunsaker_h_010; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts E to K" and "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts S to Z"
      - Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio: 1. Joseph T. Wearn, M.D., Dean, School of Medicine, and Professor, and Director, Department of Medicine; 2. Joseph T. Wearn, M.D.; 1. Dr. Ham; 2. Dr. Ham, hunsaker_h_011; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - John Maddox, Vice-President, Fuller, Smith and Ross, Cleveland, Ohio, hunsaker_h_012; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Area Project Committee Meeting Cleveland, 03/15/1954; hunsaker_h_013; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Area Project Committee Meeting Cleveland, 03/15/1954; hunsaker_h_014; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of Virginia: 1. George B. Zehmer, Director Extension Division; 2. Jess & Jean Ogden, Community Services, Extension Division, hunsaker_h_015; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of Virginia: 1. George B. Zehmer, Director Extension Division; 2. Jess & Jean Ogden, Community Services, Extension Division, 03/02/1954; hunsaker_h_016; 4 inch Blue Soundscriber Disc (Box 13)
      - Ernest A. Lowe, Associate Director, University of Georgia Center for Continuing Education, Athens, GA., 02/27/1954; hunsaker_h_017; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of Georgia: 1. William A. King, District Agent Agriculture Extension and William A. Sutton, State 4H Club Leader, Agricultural Extension; 2. Tommy L. Walton, Community Development Specialist, Assistant Agricultural Economist, Agricultural Extension, 02/26/1954; hunsaker_h_018; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview may be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts S to Z"
      - John E. Ivey, JR, Director, Southern Regional Education Board, Atlanta, Georgia, 02/25/1954; hunsaker_h_019; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview may be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts E to K"
      - University of Georgia, Athens, GA: 1. Omer C. Aderhold, President; 2. Omer C. Aderhold, 02/24/1954; hunsaker_h_020; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview may be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D"
      - University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia: 1. Barnett O. Williams, Professor of Sociology and Head of the Department; 2. Barnett O. Williams, 02/24/1954; hunsaker_h_021; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL: 1. William L. Leap, Professor of Social Work, School of Social Welfare, and Vernon Fox, Associate Professor of Social Welfare, School of Social Welfare; 2. A. B. Martin, Vice-President, FSU, hunsaker_h_022; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL: 1. Henry F. Becker, Professor Geography; 2. J. Broward Culpepper, Extension Secretary, Florida Board of Control of Higher Education, hunsaker_h_023; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of of Florida, Gainesville, FL: 1. Irving L. Webber, Assistant Professor Sociology and Anthropology; 2. Chief Joiner, Chief of Police, Gainesville, FL, hunsaker_h_024; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of Florida, Gainesville, FL: Seminar on Community Planning at the University of Florida; William T. Arnett, Dean of the College of Architecture and Allied Arts, is presiding and conducting the meeting; speech by T. Lynn, hunsaker_h_025; Seminar on Community Planning at the University of Florida; More information with recording. Mr. Arnett is presiding and conducting the meeting; speech by T. Lynn; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - University of Florida, Gainesville, FL: 1. Hollis Rinehart, Chairman, Florida Board of Control for Higher Education, Miami, FL; 2. William T. Arnett, Dean of the College of Architecture and Allied Arts, hunsaker_h_026; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview with Hollis Rinehart can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts L to R"
      - 1. Rheinhold P. Wolff, Professor of Economics and Director of the Bureau of Business and Economic Research, University of Miami, Coral Gables, FL; 2. Howard W. Odun, Professor of Sociology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, hunsaker_h_027; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview with Howard Odun can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts L to R"
      - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina: 1. Henry Clark (M.D.), Administrative Head, Division of Health Affairs; 2. Howard W. Odun, Professor of Sociology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, 02/11/1954; hunsaker_h_028; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview with Henry Clark can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D". Transcripts for the interview with Howard Odun can be found in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts L to R"
      - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina: 1. Albert Coates, Director, The Institute for Government, UNC Chapel Hill; 2. Rex Winslow, Director of the Bureau of Business Research, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, 02/11/1954; hunsaker_h_029; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interview with Albert Coates can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D"
      - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina: 1. George L. Simpson JR., Professor of Sociology Department, University of North Carolina; End of Interview with Gordon W. Blackwell, Director, Instructor for Research in Social Science; 2. Gordon Blackwell, 02/10/1954; hunsaker_h_030; 1. Interview with Simpson Sociology Department University of North Carolina; End of Interview with Gordon Blackwell which began on side #2 on record #1; 2. Interview with Gordon Blackwell began on side 2 and continued from 24 minutes on side #1; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
        Transcripts for the interviews can be found in Herbert C. Hunsaker, in the folder "Hunsaker DT INTV Transcripts A to D"